Register to the Reverend Stefan Liashevskii Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Stefan Liashevskii papers
1935-1982.
2008C42
Hoover Institution Archives
2 microfilm reels (0.3 linear feet)
Correspondence, speeches and writings, and photographs, relating to the Russian Orthodox Church and Russian émigré affairs.
Liashevskii, Stefan.
Access
The collection is open for research
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by Hoover Institution Archives in 2008
Alternative Forms of Material Available
A portion of the collection is available on Microfilm
Location of Originals
In part, Holy Trinity Orthodox Seminary, Jordanville, New York
Chronology
1899 June 17 Born, Taganrog, Russia
19??-1934 Faculty, Novocherkassk Tekhnikum, USSR
1934-1936 Senior geologist, Azov-Black Sea Trust, Rostov-on-Don, USSR
1936-1939 Imprisoned in Siberian concentration camp
1939 Senior geologist, Krasnodar', USSR
1943 Ordained to priesthood, Taganrog, Russia
1947 Author, Pervoe velikoe tysiacheletie Author, Pervye liudi na zemle, po Bibleiskomu skazaniiu i dannym sovremennoi arkheologii
1953 Author, Prepodobnyi German Aliaskinskii
1960 Author, Pervonachal'naia vetkhozavetnaia tserkov' v svete noveishikh raskopok i issledovanii
1977 Author, Doistoricheskaia Rus': istoriko-arkheolo-gicheskoe issledovanie
1986 Died, Augusta, ME
Scope and Content of Collection
These papers reflect the writings, papers and research interests of Stefan Liashevskii, a geologist in the USSR, archpriest of the Russian Orthodox Church, biblical scholar, and historian in emigration. Stefan Liashevskii had close relations with a number of Russian Orthodox hierarchs, which is reflected in his Correspondence File. Among his correspondents were Patriarch Aleksii (Simanskii), Metropolitan Iosif (Chernov) and Metropolitan Nikolai (Eremin).
The Speeches and Writings FILE includes several historical essays and articles dedicated to ecclesiastical figures known personally by Liashevskii in Russia and in emigration, such as Patriarch Tikhon (Belavin), Metropolitan Serafim (Lade), Hieromonk Sofronii (Sakharov) and others.
Detailed processing and preservation microfilming for these materials were made possible by a generous grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and by matching funds from the Hoover Institution and the Holy Trinity Seminary. The grant also provides depositing a microfilm copy in the Hoover Institution Archives. The original materials remain in the Holy Trinity Seminary Archives as its property. A transfer table indicating corresponding box and reel numbers is appended to this register. Any views, findings, conclusions or recommendations expressed in these materials do not necessarily represent those of the National Endowment for the Humanities.
Biography
Stefan Liashevskii was born in Taganrog, Russia, on June 17, 1899, and educated at the Novecherkassk tekhnikum, graduating in 1934. He worked as senior geologist for the Azov-Black Sea Trust in Rostov-on-Don until he was arrested in 1936 and imprisoned in a Siberian concentration camp for three years. On his release, Liashevskii returned to working as geologist. In 1943, however, he was ordained to the priesthood by the Russian Orthodox Church. As the Reverend Stefan Liashevskii, he immigrated to Germany in 1944, where he served in various parishes of the Russian Orthodox Church outside Russia, including the Saint Prokopius church in Lübeck. Liashevskii arrived in the United States in 1957 and served briefly in the jurisdiction of the Moscow Patriarchate before being assigned to a parish in Maine under the auspices of the Russian Orthodox Church outside Russia. He was also a biblical scholar, historian and writer, publishing several works on various topics, including biblical archeology and lives of the saints.
Reverend Stefan Liashevskii died in 1986 in Augusta, Maine.
Russians--United States.; Russkaia pravoslavnaia tserkov'.
- Biographical File, 1942-1976. (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes ecclesiastical and immigration documents. Arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - General, 1956-1976. (Folder 1: 1)
    Includes certificate from Russian American Scholars, and letter of recommendation
  - Conference participation, 1950-1951. (Folder 1: 2)
  - Ecclesiastical certificates, 1942-1970 (Folder 1: 3)
  - Immigration and Naturalization application, 1952 (Folder 1: 4)
- Correspondence, 1944-1982 and undated.
  Cards and letters, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
  - General, 1974-1982 and undated (Folder 1: 5)
  - Aleksii (Simanskii), Patriarch, 1962-1964 (Folder 1: 6)
  - Amvrosii (Pogodin), Arkhimandrite, 1979 and undated (Folder 1: 7)
  - Dvorzhitskaia, Irina, 1960 (Folder 1: 8)
  - Ioann (Garklavs), Archbishop, 1977-1980 and undated (Folder 1: 9)
  - Ioann (Venliand), Metropolitan, 1962-1980 and undated (Folder 1: 10)
  - Iosif (Chernov), Metropolitan, 1963-1975 and undated (Folder 1: 11)
  - Nikolai (Eremin), Metropolitan, 1956-1982 (Folder 1: 12)
  - Rimskii-Korsakov, Vladimir, 1960 (Folder 1: 13)
  - Russian Orthodox Church
    - General, 1950-1983 and undated (Folder 1: 14)
    - Decrees, and related, 1946-1976 and undated (Folder 1: 15)
  - Serafim (Lade), Metropolitan, 1944-1946 (Folder 1: 16)
  - Sofronii (Sakharov), Hieromonk, 1952-1953. (Folder 1: 17)
    Includes two photographs
  - Tolstoi, Ivan Mikhailovich, 1982 (Folder 1: 18)
  - Vladimir Kirillovich, Grand Duke, 1949-1982 and undated (Folder 1: 19)
- Speeches and Writings, 1948-1978 and undated.
  Articles, drafts, monographs, notes, pamphlets, and sermons, arranged chronologically by title
  - General
    - Articles, 1961 and undated (Folder 1: 20)
    - Essays, undated. (Folder 1: 21)
      Typescripts
    - Notebooks, undated. (Folder 1: 22-23)
      Holograph
    - Notes, undated. (Folder 1: 24)
    - Untitled, undated. (Folder 1: 25)
  - "Batiushka otets Iosiia (Sviashchenno-arkhimandrit Iosiia, nastoiatel' Taganrogskogo podvoriia Staro-Afonskogo Panteleimonovskogo monastyria),", undated. (Box-folder 2: 1)
    Typescript
  - "Gosudar' Muchenik,", undated.
    General note
    See "Pokhval'noe slovo tsartsvennym strastoterptsam"
  - Letopis' Serafimo-Diveevskogo monastyria s 1903 g. po 1927 g. Chast' vtoraia, undated. (Folder 2: 2)
    Typescript. Includes related correspondence
  - "Mitropolich'i okruga,", undated. (Folder 2: 3)
    Typescript. Includes related notes
  - "Mitropolit Serafim i nemetskoe Pravoslavie,", undated. (Folder 2: 4)
  - "O triipostasnom Boge,", undated. (Folder 2: 5)
  - "Pokhval'noe slovo tsartsvennym strastoterptsam,", undated. (Folder 2: 6)
    Typescript. Includes "Gosudar' Muchenik," undated. Typescript
  - "The tomb of our Forefather Noah the Righteous,", undated. (Folder 2: 7)
    Typescript. Includes incomplete version in Russian
  - "Vladyka Arsenii (Arkhiepiskop Rostovskii i Taganrogskii),", undated. (Folder 2: 8)
  - "Pervomu s"ezdu pravoslavnykh nemtsev v gor. Gersbruke,", 1948. (Folder 2: 9)
  - "The six days of creation,", 1948. (Folder 2: 10)
  - "Tsarstvo chetyrekh serafimov,", 1948. (Folder 2: 11)
  - "Sviataia plashchanitsa Gospodnia,", 1949. (Folder 2: 12)
  - "Mitropolit Petrogradskii Serafim (Chichagov),", 1950. (Folder 2: 13)
    Printed copy and typescript
  - "Nastavlenie sestram Bogorodichnoi obiteli v g. Liubeke o molitve i monasheskom uklade zhizni,", 1950. (Folder 2: 14)
  - "Tserkvi lukavnuiushchikh,", 1951. (Folder 2: 15)
  - "Vtoroe tysiacheletie (2 chast' 'Tsarstva Chetyrekh Serafimov'),", 1951. (Folder 2: 16)
  - "Ego sviateishestvo Patriarkh Tikhon," Sviet, 1952 May 15. (Folder 2: 17)
    Printed copy
  - "Russkie pravoslavnye tserkvi zagranitsei. Chast' I,", 1953. (Folder 2: 18)
  - "Zakliuchenie ob inzhenerno-geologicheskikh usloviiakh stroitel'nogo uchastka Trekhsviatitel'skoi tserkvi,", 1954. (Folder 2: 19)
  - "Pravoslavnaia tserkov' sredi narodov zapada,", 1955. (Folder 2: 20)
  - "Pervonachal'naia vetkhozavetnaia Tserkov' (ot Adama do Avraama) v svete noveishikh raskopok,", 1957. (Folder 2: 21)
  - "Tsarstvo nebesnoe,", 1976. (Folder 2: 22)
  - "Dogmat o Edinosushchnoi, Zhivotvoriashchei i Nerazdel'noi Troitse,", 1978. (Folder 2: 23)
- Subject File, 1954-1973 and undated.
  Certificates, clippings, correspondence, and notes, arranged alphabetically by subject
  - Biblical archeology, 1966-1973 and undated. (Folder 2: 24)
    Includes clippings and typed notes
  - Roman Catholic Church--Relics, 1954-1970. (Folder 2: 25)
    Certificates
  - Velesova kniga
    - Correspondence, 1970-1973 and undated (Folder 2: 26)
    - Newspaper articles, 1967-1973 and undated (Folder 2: 27)
    - Notes, undated. (Folder 2: 28)
      Holograph and typescript
- Photographs, 1935-1973 and undated. (Box 3)
  Not filmed.
  - Iosif (Chernov), Metropolitan, 1935-1973. (Folder 3: 1)
    8 prints
  - Sofronii (Sakharov).
    See Correspondence/Sofronii (Sakharov)
  - Stefan Liashevskii, Reverend
    - General, undated. (Folder 3: 2)
    - Parishes served, 1943-1969 and undated. (Folder 3: 3-4)
      160 prints in two albums
  - One print of an unidentified hierarch, undated (Folder 3: 5)